<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Python on Adrián Abreu</title><link>https://adrianabreu.com/tags/python/</link><description>Recent content in Python on Adrián Abreu</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>es-ES</language><copyright>2017-2024 Adrián Abreu powered by Hugo and Kiss Theme</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 13 Aug 2024 07:00:32 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://adrianabreu.com/tags/python/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Finding pet projects</title><link>https://adrianabreu.com/blog/2024-08-13-finding-pet-projects/</link><pubDate>Tue, 13 Aug 2024 07:00:32 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adrianabreu.com/blog/2024-08-13-finding-pet-projects/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;As my company undergoes layoffs, I&amp;rsquo;m back on the job hunt. While I&amp;rsquo;m in the field of data, I often find myself missing the hands-on experience that comes from personal projects. I realized that I&amp;rsquo;m not practicing all the skills I need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During a recent interview, I was asked about my experience with sending reports via email—something I hadn’t done in a few years. That got me thinking: could I turn this into a pet project?&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Querying the databricks api</title><link>https://adrianabreu.com/blog/2024-01-26-querying-the-databricks-api/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 Jan 2024 09:06:32 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adrianabreu.com/blog/2024-01-26-querying-the-databricks-api/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Exploring databricks SQL usage&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At my company, we adopted databricks SQL for most of our users. Some users have developed applications that use the JDBC connector, some users have built their dashboards, and some users write plain ad-hoc queries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We wanted to know what they queried, so we tried to use Unity Catalog&amp;rsquo;s insights, but it wasn&amp;rsquo;t enough for our case. We work with IOT and we are interested in what filters they apply within our tables.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Configurando poetry y gitlab</title><link>https://adrianabreu.com/blog/2020-12-30-configurando-poetry-gitlab/</link><pubDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2020 15:42:32 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adrianabreu.com/blog/2020-12-30-configurando-poetry-gitlab/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Hace poco más de un mes cambié de trabajo y me encontré además con un cambio de stack considerable. Ahora estoy trabajando con aws + github + python. Y bueno, al margen de los cambios de conceptos y demás, me ha llevado bastante encontrar un flujo de trabajo que no me pareciera &amp;ldquo;frágil&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lo primero y que me ha decepcionado bastante es que github no incluye soporte para hostear paquetes de python. Lo tendrá sí, pero sin fecha clara y &lt;a href="https://github.com/github/roadmap/projects/1?card_filter_query=label%3Apackages"&gt;por lo pronto parece que será despues de Junio de 2021&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>