<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Firebase on Adrián Abreu</title><link>https://adrianabreu.github.io/tags/firebase/</link><description>Recent content in Firebase on Adrián Abreu</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>es-ES</language><copyright>2017-2022 Adrián Abreu powered by Hugo and Kiss Theme</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2022 07:28:32 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://adrianabreu.github.io/tags/firebase/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Reading firebase data</title><link>https://adrianabreu.github.io/blog/2022-07-01-reading-firebase-data/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2022 07:28:32 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adrianabreu.github.io/blog/2022-07-01-reading-firebase-data/</guid><description>Firebase is a common component nowadays for most mobile apps. And it can provide some useful insights, for example in my previous company we use it to detect where the people left at the initial app wizard. (We could measure it).
It is quite simple to export your data to BigQuery: https://firebase.google.com/docs/projects/bigquery-export
But maybe your lake is in AWS or Azure. In the next lines, I will try to explain how to load the data in your lake and some improvements we have applied.</description></item><item><title>Exportando los datos de firebase</title><link>https://adrianabreu.github.io/blog/2021-05-06-exporting-firebase-data/</link><pubDate>Thu, 06 May 2021 11:49:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adrianabreu.github.io/blog/2021-05-06-exporting-firebase-data/</guid><description>Si trabajamos analizando los datos de una aplicación móvil es muy probable que esté integrado algún sistema para trackear los eventos de la app. Y entre ellos, uno de los más conocidos es Firebase.
Estos eventos contienen mucha información útil y nos permiten por ejemplo saber, un usuario que se ha ido cuanto tiempo ha usado la aplicación o cuantos dias han pasado.
O si realmente ha seguido el flujo de acciones que esperabamos (con un diagrama de sankey podríamos ver donde se han ido los usuarios).</description></item></channel></rss>