<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Delta on Adrián Abreu</title><link>https://adrianabreu.github.io/tags/delta/</link><description>Recent content in Delta on Adrián Abreu</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>es-ES</language><copyright>2017-2022 Adrián Abreu powered by Hugo and Kiss Theme</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 02 Oct 2023 13:25:32 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://adrianabreu.github.io/tags/delta/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Repairing metadata unity catalog</title><link>https://adrianabreu.github.io/blog/2023-10-02-repairing-metadata-unity-catalog/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 Oct 2023 13:25:32 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adrianabreu.github.io/blog/2023-10-02-repairing-metadata-unity-catalog/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been subscribed to https://www.dataengineeringweekly.com/p/data-engineering-weekly-148 for years. This last number included several on-call posts on Medium. I found these quite useful.
Today, I got an alert from Metaplane that a cost monitor dashboard was out of date. I checked the processes, and everything was fine. I ran a query to check the freshness of the data and it was ok too.
Metaplane checks our delta table freshness by querying the table information available in the Unity Catalog.</description></item><item><title>Duplicates with delta, how can it be?</title><link>https://adrianabreu.github.io/blog/2023-03-20-delta-duplicates/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Mar 2023 09:50:32 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adrianabreu.github.io/blog/2023-03-20-delta-duplicates/</guid><description>Long time without writing! On highlights: I left my job at Schwarz It in December last year, and now I&amp;rsquo;m a full-time employee at Wallbox! I&amp;rsquo;m really happy with my new job, and I&amp;rsquo;ve experienced interesting stuff. This one was just one of these strange cases where you start doubting the compiler.
Context One of my main tables represents sensor measures from our chargers with millisecond precision. The numbers are quite high, we are talking over 2 billion rows per day.</description></item></channel></rss>